A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Speeches, Addresses, Articles by Alderman
  - n.d. Message of Congratulations to a group of thirty year old veterans of teaching at Chapel Hill, North Carolina, typescript (Box-folder 28:27)
  - n.d. Speech concerning the South probably for a northern audience, typescript (Box-folder 28:28)
  - n.d. Speech "Christ the Leader" [possibly for the mass meeting of the Federation of Men's Bible Classes in Richmond, Virginia, on November 12, 1911?], typescript (Box-folder 28:29)
  - n.d. Speech concerning Philanthropy delivered at Goldsboro, North Carolina, manuscript (Box-folder 28:30)
  - n.d. Address to Yale Matriculates, typescript (Box-folder 29:1)
  - n.d. Speech concerning a Co-ordinate College for Women, typescript (Box-folder 29:2)
  - n.d. Thank you from Alderman to Judge Sinclair, the Committee, and citizens of Charlottesville for the [unnamed] gift, typescript (Box-folder 29:3)
  - n.d. Speech draft concerning the State, manuscript (Box-folder 29:4)
  - n.d. Draft and Notes for Speech "The Southern Boy and His Opportunity" (Box-folder 29:5)
  - n.d. Speech concerning the Southern Education Board and the Conference for Education in the South, typescript (Box-folder 29:6)
  - n.d. Notes for a Speech on building character and education, while at [North Carolina?], manuscript (Box-folder 29:7)
  - n.d. Speech concerning the expectation for students at the University of Virginia, manuscript (Box-folder 29:8)
  - n.d. Article concerning the need for dormitories "Housing Problem is Endangering University Spirit" written by Charles S. Trimmer for Alderman's approval and signature and to appear in The Outlook, typescript (Box-folder 29:9)
  - n.d. Notes for a speech on the progress and needs of the University of Virginia (Box-folder 29:10)
  - n.d. Drafts of Speeches concerning democracy and education (Box-folder 29:11)
  - n.d. Notes and Drafts for talks on "What is College Life?" or "What is College For?" (Box-folder 29:12)
  - n.d. Notes for welcoming addresses to students (Box-folder 29:13)
  - n.d. Greetings to the Alumni (Box-folder 29:14)
  - n.d. Notes on Shakespeare by Alderman (Box-folder 29:15)
  - n.d. Speech fragments concerning education (Box-folder 29:16)
  - ca. 1912-1926, n.d. Speeches - Memoranda, Statements, Miscellaneous Notes, and Quotations concerning: oratorical contest held by the Richmond Times Dispatch; the quality of a University dependent upon quality of its alumni; Thomas Jefferson; Dissertations; Democracy and the Y.M.C.A.; the Educated Man; Scribner's article on "The Felicities of a College President"; the Ems telegram; Act concerning servants and slaves (Box-folder 29:17)
  - n.d. Notes and Materials for Miscellaneous University of Virginia Speeches, manuscript and printed (Box-folder 29:18)
  - n.d. Speeches - Incomplete and fragmentary (Box-folder 29:19)
- Series IV: Scrapbooks and Notecards
  - Ca. 1908, 1921-1929 Scrapbook of News clippings concerning Alderman and the University of Virginia; also obituary of Dr. Wallace Buttrick (pages are loose) (Box-folder 29:20)
  - n.d. Box of 4 x 6 inch note cards of Edwin A. Alderman's speeches, addresses, and articles in chronological order, chiefly typewritten (Box-folder 30:1)
  - n.d. Box of 4 x 6 inch note cards of Edwin A. Alderman's speeches, addresses, and articles in chronological order, chiefly hand-written (Box-folder 31:1)
  - Scrapbook: 1864, 1877-1905 Early career of Edwin A. Alderman, including Bethel Academy, North Carolina teaching career, President of North Carolina and Tulane University, election as President of the University of Virginia, pages are very fragile and loose (Oversize) (Oversize 1)
  - Scrapbook: 1877, 1897-1925 News clippings and Printed Material concerning: Bethel Academy School Records, announcement for wedding to Bessie Hearn, speeches and public appearances, chiefly not at the University of Virginia, material about Woodrow Wilson probably used in Alderman's Memorial Speech about him (Oversize 2)
  - Scrapbook: 1907, 1916-1929 Correspondence and News clippings concerning the war work of Bessie Alderman with the American Fund For French Wounded, the death of James McConnell, the trip to Europe in 1926; Correspondents include: Richard E. Byrd (1926); Alfred E. Smith (January 18, 1929); Harry F. Byrd (December 12, [1928] and June 18, 1929); Alice Vincent Massey (April 5, 1929) (Oversize 3)
  - Scrapbook: 1928-1931, 1933 Correspondence, Programs, and News clippings, including the wedding of Ann Polk Cuculla and Edwin A. Alderman, Jr., Alderman's 25 th Anniversary at the University of Virginia, American Academy of Arts and Letters; Correspondents include: Abby Rockefeller (July 5, 1929); Marguerite Wilbur (October 29); Ormond V. Gould (n.d.); W.W. Fuller (March 22, 31, 1930); Anne O'Hare McCormick (June 27, 1930); George E. Vincent (April 14, 1930); Edward A. Filene (April 26, 1931); John Randolph Bolling (April 25, 1930); Eleanor Roosevelt (June 3, 1933); George Foster Peabody (July 16, 1931) (Oversize 4)
  - Scrapbook: 1890-1932 News clippings, Programs, Postcards, and Correspondence; Correspondents include: W.W. Fuller (July 17, 1931); Edith K. Roosevelt (August 11, 1931); Eleanor Roosevelt (July 16, 1931; November 12, 1932); Burton J. Hendrick (December 3, 1931); Frank Porter Graham, President of the University of North Carolina (December 2, 1931); Eleanor S. Buchanan (March 22, 1932); and A. Lawrence Lowell (November 28, 1932) (Oversize 5)
  - Scrapbook: 1924, 1931 Chiefly News clippings concerning Woodrow Wilson Memorial Speech by Edwin A. Alderman and Correspondence about the death of Edwin A. Alderman, Correspondents including: Gamaliel Bradford (September 9, 1931); Mrs. E.M. House (October 15); George Gordon Battle (November 15, 1931); Alice W. Page (July 3, 1931); Billy Noble (September 1, 1931); William E. Dodd (August 23, 1931); and W.W. Fuller (November 13, 1931) (Oversize 6)
  - Scrapbook: 1931 News clippings and Printed concerning the death of Edwin A. Alderman (Oversize 7)
  - Scrapbook: 1931 Chiefly Telegrams concerning the death of Edwin A. Alderman and Photographs of the Gravesite (Oversize 8)